The Sabbateni Collection of Renaissance Music Manuscripts MSS.239
Fales Library and Special Collections
The Sabbateni Collection of Renaissance Music Manuscripts
circa 1600
Fales Library and Special Collections
Fales Library
MSS.239
31 Volumes in 13 parts
The Sabbateni collection contains printed and manuscript music in 13 parts bound into 31 volumes, for the use of a four-part chorus in Prague, circa 1603-1604.
Provenance
The volumes were purchased in 1999.
Scope and Content
The Sabbateni collection contains printed and manuscript music parts bound into 31 volumes, for the use of a four-part chorus in Prague, circa 1603-1604.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Music -- 17th century.; Music -- Manuscripts.
- Bound Volumes
  - Sabbateni 1 (formerly A.1), circa 1600
    Scope and Content
    Six manuscripts bound together, with a total of 115 works
    Four part-books: Discantus, Tenor, Altus, Sextus, of a set of at least six
    - Altus (Box 1)
    - Discantus (Box 2)
    - Tenor (Box 3)
    - Sextus (Box 4)
  - Sabbateni 2 (formerly A.2), circa 1600
    A single manuscript, with 38 works
    Two partbooks, Discantus and Quintus, from a set of five
    - Discantus (Box 5)
    - Quintus (Box 6)
  - Sabbateni 3 (formerly A.3), circa 1600
    Two manuscripts, bound together with a total of 109 works
    Two part-books, Discantus and Bassus, from a set of at least six
    - Discantus (Box 7)
    - Bassus (Box 8)
  - Sabbateni 4 (formerly A.4), circa 1600
    Three manuscripts bound together, with a total of 91 works
    One part-book, Bassus, from a set, probably of six
    - Bassus (Box 9)
  - Sabbateni 5 (formerly B.1), circa 1600
    Five editions, bound together
    (1): Thesaurus Musicus [I] (Nürnberg: Montanus & Neuber, 1564) RISM 15641: T; T2; B2
    (2): Thesauri Musici II (Nürnberg: Montanus & Neuber, 1564) RISM 15642: T; 5; 7
    (3): Thesauri Musici III (Nürnberg: Montanus & Neuber, 1564) RISM 15643: T; Vag
    (4): Thesauri Musici IV (Nürnberg: Montanus & Neuber, 1564) RISM 15644: T; Vag
    (5): Thesauri Musici V (Nürnberg: Montanus & Neuber, 1564) RISM 15645: T
    - Bassus Secundus (Box 10)
    - Tenor (Box 11)
    - Tenor Secundus (Box 12)
  - Sabbateni 6 (formerly B.2), circa 1600
    Nine editions, bound together
    (1): Lassus: Cantiones Sacrae à6 (München: Heinrich, 1601) RISM 16013
    (2): Reiner: LIber Mottetarum à6,8 (München: Heinrich, 1600) RISM R1086
    (3): Agricola, J.: Motetae novae à4-8 (Nürnberg: Agricola, 1601) RISM A432
    (4): Demantius: Trias Precum Vesperinarum à4-6 (Nürnberg: Agricola, [1602]) RISM D1533
    (5): Franck, M.: I Sacrarum Melodiarum à4-8 (Augsburg: Schönigk, 1601) RISM F1641
    (6): Hassler, J.: Madrigali à6 (Nürnberg: Kaufmann, 1600) RISM H2345
    (7): Aichinger: Liber Sacrarum Cantionum à5-8 (Nürnberg: Kauffmann, 1597) RISM A519
    (8): Hausmann: Manipulus Sacrarum Cantionum à5-6 (Nürnberg: Kauffmann, 1602) RISM H2377
    (9): Aichinger: Odaria Lectissima à3-4 (Augsburg: Willer (Praetorius), 1601) RISM A5244
    Three part-books, Camtus, Altus and Tenor, from a set of at least six, probably eight
    - Cantus (Box 13)
    - Altus (Box 14)
    - Tenor (Box 15)
  - Sabbateni 7 (formerly B.3), circa 1600
    Separated Materials
    (1): H. Praetorius: Cantiones Sacrae à5-8 (Hamburg: de Ohr, 1599) RISM P5336
    (2): Vulpius: Cantionum Sacrarum à6-8+ (Jena: Richtzenhan, 1602) RISM V2569
    (3): Magnificat Octo tonorum diversorum à4-8,12 (Nürnberg: Kauffmann, 1600) RISM 16001
    (4): manuscript, with 12 works.
    Four part-books: Cantus,Bassus, Quintus and Septimus, from a set probably of eight
    - Cantus (Box 16)
    - Bassus (Box 17)
    - Quintus (Box 18)
    - Septimus (Box 19)
  - Sabbateni 8 (formerly B.4), circa 1600
    Four editions, bound together:
    (1): Lassus: Fasciculi Aliquot Sacrarum Cantionum à4-6,8 (Nürnberg: Gerlach, 1589) RISM L991
    (2): Continuatio Cantionum Sacrarum à4-8+ (Nürnberg: Gerlach, 1588) RISM 15882
    (3): Corollarium Cantionum Sacrarum à5-8+ (Nürnberg: Gerlach, 1588) RISM 15905
    (4): Handl: Moralia à5,6,8 (Nürnberg: Alexander, 1588) RISM H1988
    Three part-books, Cantus, Tenor and Altus, from a set of eight
    - Cantus (Box 20)
    - Tenor (Box 21)
    - Altus (Box 22)
  - Sabbateni 9 (formerly B.5), circa 1600
    One edition and one manuscript, bound together
    (1): Lassus: Fasciculi ALiquot Sacrarum Cantionum à4-6,8 (Nürnberg: Gerlach: 1589) RISM L991
    (2): manuscript, with 11 works.
    Two part-books, Altus and Bassus, from a set probably of eight
    Music -- 17th century.; Music -- Manuscripts.
    - Altus (Box 23)
    - Bassus (Box 24)
  - Sabbateni 10 (formerly B.6), circa 1600
    The four editions of the works of Jacobus Gallus Handl
    (1): Handl: I Operis Musici (Prag: Nigrin, 1587) RISM H1980
    (2): Handl: II Operis Musici (Prag: Nigrin, 1587) RISM H1981
    (3): Handl: III Operis Musici (Prag: Nigrin, 1587) RISM H1982
    (4): Handl: IV Operis Musici (Prag: Nigrin, 1590) RISM H1985
    Two part-books, Cantus and Tenor, from a set of six
    - Cantus (Box 25)
    - Tenor (Box 26)
  - Sabbateni 11(formerly B.7), circa 1600
    Five editions with a manuscript appendix, bound together
    (1): Sacrae Symphoniae à4-16, ed. K. Hassler (Nürnberg: Kauffmann, 1601) RISM 16012
    (2): Sacrarum Symphoniarum Continuatio à4-12 (Nürnberg: Kauffmann, 1600) RISM 16002
    (3): Hassler: Sacri Concentus à4-12 (Augsburg: Schönigk, 1601) RISM H2328
    (4): Praetorius: Magnificat à8, Motetis à8,12 (Hamburg: de Ohr, 1602) RISM P5333
    (5): Gumpelzhaimer: I Sacrorum Cantionum à8 (Augsburg: Schönigk, 1601) RISM G5139
    (6): Manuscript appendix of one work.
    Three part-books, Cantus, Tenor and Septimus, from a set, probably of twelve
    - Septima Vox (Box 27)
    - Cantus (Box 28)
    - Tenor (Box 31)
  - Sabbateni 12 (formerly B.8), circa 1600
    Three editions, bound together
    (1): Pottier: Selectissimarum Missarum Flores à4-6+ (Antwerp: Phalese, 1599) RISM 15991
    (2): Regnart: Missae Sacrae à5-8 (Frankfurt: Richter (Stein), 1602) RISM R734
    (3): Pevernage: Cantiones Sacrae à6-8 (Frankfurt: Richter (Stein), 1602) RISM P1675
    One part-book, the Sexta Vox, from a set, probably of eight
    - Sexta Vox (Box 29)
  - Sabbateni 13 (formerly B.9)
    (1): Neander, A.: I Sacrarum cantionum à4-8,10,12 (Frankfurt: Stein, 1605) RISM N308
    (2): Neander, A.: II Sacrarum cantionum à4-8,10,12,14,24 (Frankfurt: Stein, 1605) RISM N309
    (3): Neander, A.: III Sacrarum cantionum à4-8,10,12,14,24 (Frankfurt: Stein, 1606) RISM N310
    (4): Bonhomme: Melodiae sacrae à5,6,8,9 (Frankfurt: Stein, 1605) RISM B3469
    (5): Reiner, J.: Gloriosissimae Virginis ... Mariae canticum à8 (Frankfurt: Stein, 1604) RISM R1091
    (6): Regnart: I Sacrarum cantionum à4-8,10,12 (Frankfurt: Stein, 1604) RISM R737
    (7): Schramm: Cantiones selectae à5,6,8 (Frankfurt: Stein, 1606) RISM S2109
    (8): Bendinello: I Sacrarum cantionum à4-5 (Frankfurt: Stein, 1604) RISM B1911
    (9): Bendinello: II Sacrarum cantionum à5 (Frankfurt: Stein, 1604) RISM B1912=16044
    One part-book, the Cantus, from a set of twelve
    - Cantus (Box 30)